Guide to the Jewish Communal Registers (Pinkese kehilah) Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Jewish communal registers (Pinkese kehilah) collection
1623-1960
MS 1824
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
70.42
(61 boxes)
The collection consists of register books of various Jewish communal organizations, mainly in Europe, with a few from the Middle East and the United States. The volumes include minute books of synagogues and social welfare committees, account books, school registers, and wills. They document the activities, concerns, and conditions of Jewish communities, as well as their relations with neighbors and governmental authorities. The registers include genealogical, sociological, and historical information.
Fuhrmann, Simon
Ezras Torah (Organization)
Hevrah Tehilim Bikur holim u-mishmorim Bet ha-Keneset Stefani Ortodoks ( Pinkas kehilat Bet ha-Keneset Stefani)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The registers were purchased by the Judaica Collection and transferred to Manuscripts and Archives, 2002-2015. Most of the registers were purchased from Yeshayahu Vinograd, Jerusalem, 2002-2003. One was purchased at auction from Kestenbaum & Company, New York, in 2002. Others were purchased from Bery Gross, New York, in 2003. Additional registers were purchased 2004-2008 from Bery Gross, New York, and Yeshayahu Vinograd and Moshe Rosenfeld, Jerusalem. One was purchased from Kestenbaum & Company on the Rosalyn and Joseph Newman Collection Fund, 2015.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as received from the Judaica Collection.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of register books of various Jewish communal organizations, mainly in Europe, with a few from the Middle East and the United States. The volumes include minute books of synagogues and social welfare committees, account books, school registers, and wills. They document the activities, concerns, and conditions of Jewish communities, as well as their relations with neighbors and governmental authorities. The registers include genealogical, sociological, and historical information.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Jews -- Austria -- Vienna -- History -- Sources; Jews -- England -- History -- Sources; Jews -- France -- Alsace -- History -- Sources; Jews -- Germany -- Frankfurt -- History -- Sources; Jews -- Hungary -- History -- Sources; Jews -- Jerusalem -- History -- Sources; Jews -- Italy -- Lugo -- History -- Sources; Jews -- Lebanon -- Beirut -- History -- Sources; Jews -- Netherlands -- Borculo -- History -- Sources; Jews -- Palestine -- History -- Sources; Jews -- Poland -- History -- Sources; Jews -- Romania -- History -- Sources; Jews -- Slovakia -- History -- Sources; Jews -- Slovakia -- Ardovo -- History -- Sources; Jews -- Turkey -- History -- Sources; Jews -- Ukraine -- History -- Sources; Jews -- New York (State) -- History -- Sources; [Account book of Ezras Torah organization]; [Alberti-Irsa, Hungary and other towns and cities in Hungary: collection of documents]; [Frankfurt Jewish community: collection of documents from the 18th century]; [Hevrah mishnayot anshe Maramarish]; [Manuscript documents regarding charities of the Jerusalem Sephardic community]; [Minutes of the Education Committee of the Jews Infant School]; 1891-1901 Jegyzökönyv..; Brody fele vegrendelet; Comune di Lugo; Froyen-grindungs-mitglieder shel ḥevrah g.ḥ.: I; Geburts-Protokoll; Ha[up]tbuch; Hatḥalat ha-protoḳollen min shenat 687 ... de-ḥevra mishnayot ṿe-talmud torah ba-ʻir Mishḳolts; Haupt Protokoll für Gemeinde Palota; Ḥeshbon bukh ... ḥevra ḳadisha Irsa; Jews Infant School: minute book; Ḳeren Ḳayemet; Ketav yad al kehilot Yehudiyot be-Eropah; Ketav-yad pinkas K.K. Shats; Ḳunṭeret shel mazkir neshamot; Libro de oro; Mahberet Yeshivat Bar-Yohai al Har Tsiyon ha-Tana ha-eloki ha-Rashbi ve-R. Elazar beno; Mindszenti izraelita "Szent-Egylet" kozgyuleseinek jegyzokonyvei 1889ik evtol.; Minutes of the Ḥevrah Ḳadisha; Miskolczi Izraelita noegylet torzskonyve: 1878ik evi Aprilis 1tol; Notulen boek der pieuse vereeniging ʻAṭeret baḥurim gemilut ḥasadim te Borculo; Pinkas: mi-bet tefilah he-hadash. pinkas kehilat Ramnicu-Sarat; Pinkas: zeh shayakh leha-hevrah Tehilim u-Vikur holim shel be. ha-kenes. Meydman Strit she-nityasdah bi-shenat 660 [1900]; Pinkas bet ha-yetomim be-Satu-Mare; Pinḳas de-ḥevrah mishnayot: ʻim ḥaluḳat ha-Sha"s.; Pinḳas ha-laz shayakh le-H.H. ha-alufim Ro.Ṭ. manhige ḳehilatenu K.K. Palaṭi ... / Ḳahal ʻAdat Yeshurun; Pinḳas ha-laz shayakh leha-ḥevrah ḳedoshah de-ḳ.ḳ. p. Ardoya ..; Pinkas hevrah kadisha Palati (Varpalota); Pinḳas ḥevrah mishnayot Mediʼash; Pinkas hevrat Ezer yoledet ha-kelali; Pinḳas ḳehilah shel Alberti-Irsa, Hungary; Pinḳas ḳehilah shel Csaba, Hungary; Pinḳas ḳehilah shel Hogyesz, Hungary; Pinkas kehilat Bet ha-Keneset Stefani; Pinkas kehilat London; Pinkas kehilat Lugo; Pinkas kehilat Mantovah; Pinkas kehilat Mishkolt︠s︡; Pinkas kehilat Ramnicu-Sarat; Pinḳas ḳehilot Alzas; Pinkas Mishnayot; Pinḳas Papa; Pinḳas proṭoḳolim shel Ḥevrah Ḳadisha (Szent-Egylet), Medgyes; Pinkas rishum kehilat Mishkolt︠s︡; Pinḳas shel ḥevrah ḳadisha gemilut ḥasadim; Hermannstadt, Sibiu (Romania); Pinḳas tsaṿaʼah ṿe-taḳanot bet ha-midrash shel R. Yosef Binyamin Zeʼev Brody; Pinkas Tsefat-650 [1890]; Pinḳese ḳehilot Ḳushṭa ṿe-Izmir; Proṭoḳol bukh de-ḥevrah baʻale takhlis de-anshe maʻamad; Protokoll ... / orth. Chewra Kadischa in Medgyes; Protokoll uber die am 10 Februar 1935 ..; Protokoll über die am 15 Juni 1922 ..; Protokoll von Todten, Trauungs, Geburts; Register book: Romania 1940-1943; Register of births 1852-1877 Vol. B; Register of Jewish community of Orsova, Romania, 1935-1951; Registru de intrare si esire; Rules and regulations, Liverpool; Schul-Cassa-Buch 1851; Sefer ha-taḳanot le-yirʼe H. meʼet ḥevrah mishnayot le-agudat ḳehal ḥasidim; Sefer ha-zikaron hevrah Ezer-yoledet; Sefer ha-zikhronot divre ha-yamim; Sefer zikaron: le-yire H. ule-hoshve shemo yitbarakh; mahberet Yeshivat Bar-Yohai al Har Tsiyon ha-Tana ha-eloki ha-Rashbi ve-R. Elazar beno; Sefer zikhronot / zot naʻasah ṿe-nikhtav ṭovatkha mimeni Hanany. ben Shelomoh Kats; Shulkasse shtand; South Hackney synagogue: minute book; Stammbuch über die durch die mediascher orth. chevra-kadisa verwalèten stiftungèn (ker̀en kajemés); Szeged, Hungary: Collection of documents relating to the Jewish community; Szuletesi Anyakonyv 1871-1875; Születési anyakonyv; Taḳanot: yeshanot ve-ḥadashot she-naʻaseh bi-retson ha-manhige ha-ḳehilah uvi-retson kol ha-b.b. de-ḳehilatenu ..; Takanoth of the Liverpool synagogue; Templul Israelit din Campina; Vienna: minutes of a Jewish women's society, 1880-1921; Zeh ha-pinḳas de-ḥevr. ḳadisha Deṿa [Bacia, Romania]; Zeh ha-pinḳas shayakh leha-ḥavirah mishnayot meha-ḳloyz Linat ha-Tsedeḳ; Zeh sefer ha-taḳanot le-yirʼe H. meʼet ḥevrah mishnayot le-agudat ḳehal ḥasidim
- Inventory, 1623-1960
  Scope and Contents
  ---Each item description begins with the title of each register:
  The title comes from (in order of preference): the title page, the cover, the page headings, the first words in the register, a name or description used by the vendor, or a descriptive title assigned by the staff of the Judaica Collection. If the title does not appear in the book itself, it is in brackets. In cases where there are one or more alternate titles, they are separated by semi-colons.
  Titles that are originally in non-Roman alphabets appear in Romanized transliterations. Use of diacritics is inconsistent.
  ---The title is followed by the place where the register was written:
  Usually the place is written as it appears in the book, or in its Romanized form. Common forms are used for well-known names (for example: New York, not Nyu-York).
  If available, the name of the place in the form authorized according to cataloging rules is added in parentheses, especially if it differs from the way the name of the place appears in the book.
  ---The date of the work appears at the end of each description:
  Hebrew dates are in numeric form according to how they appear in the register, i.e. 760 or 5760. Gregorian dates are provided in brackets for each Hebrew date. The Hebrew year 650 appears as 650, [1889-1890], since either of those two years would be possible. If the month is known, only the correct Gregorian year is provided.
  At times one year is written on the title page, but the register includes dated entries covering a span of years. In that case the Hebrew date would be written as it appears in the book, but the Gregorian dates would reflect the actual years covered in the register.
  ---Physical description is included when available. The number of pages in brackets indicates that the pages are not numbered in the book.
  ---The descriptions are based on material provided by the vendor, examination of the book, and translations by staff members.
  - Protokol bukh de-hevrah baale takhlis de-anshe maamad, 1921-1944 (Box 1)
    New York. Minutes of the Jewish Orthodox Alliance of America, Agudath Anshei Mamod. Manuscript written and typewritten mainly in Yiddish with some English. 300 pp.‚ 32 cm.
  - Sefer Zikaron: le-yire H. ule-hoshve shemo yitbarakh; mahberet Yeshivat Bar-Yohai al Har Tsiyon ha-Tana ha-eloki ha-Rashbi ve-R. Elazar beno; [Pinkas Tsefat—650], 650, [1889-1890] (Box 2)
    Tsefat. List of contributors to the yeshivah at the tomb of Simeon bar Yohai and his son, Eleazar, in Meron. Extensively illuminated title page with calligraphy and decorative borders in different shades of gold ink. In Hebrew.
  - Zeh sefer ha-takanot le-yire H. me'et hevrat mishnayot le-agudat kehal hasidim, 681, [1920-1921] (Box 2)
    Yafo. By-laws of Mishnah society of a hassidic congregation in Yafo (Jaffa/Tel Aviv, Israel). Illuminated title page and captions written in red, gold, and black ink. In Hebrew. [5] pp., 33 cm.
  - Pinkas hevrat Ezer Yoledet ha-kelali, 670, [1909-1910] (Box 2)
    Cover title: Sefer ha-zikaron hevrah Ezer-yoledet. Yerushala[y]im. Extensively illuminated, colorful title page. By-laws and membership list of an aid society for women giving birth, signed by the women who founded it with official stamps of rabbinical courts in Jerusalem. Includes names of important women in the Jerusalem's Jewish community before the creation of the state of Israel. According to the vendor, this is the only known register created by women in pre-1948 Israel. [22] pp.
  - [Manuscripts regarding charities of the Jerusalem Sephardic community]; [Halukah de-Rabanan]., 630, [1869-1870] (Box 2)
    Jerusalem. Records of distributions of charitable funds by the Sephardic rabbis of Jerusalem, as well as Hebron, Tiberias, and Jaffa. In Hebrew and Ladino. May include documents from later in the nineteenth century. 58 leaves‚ 30 cm.
  - South Hackney synagogue: minute book, 1881-1892 (Box 3)
    London. Minutes of board meetings concerning various synagogue matters, including officers, membership, holidays, the religious school, and mikveh (ritual bath). In English with some Hebrew words. On blue paper. Approx. 150 pp.; 34 cm.
  - Jews Infant School: minute book, 1843-1857 (Box 3)
    London. Minutes of board of Jewish school for children ages two to six. Includes descriptions of the challenges and accomplishments of this charitable institution in nineteenth century London. Signed by leaders of the community, including Sir Francis Henry Goldsmid and Nathaniel Montefiore. In English.
  - [Minutes of the Education Committee of the Jews Infant School], 1899-1904 (Box 3)
    London. Resolutions and actions concerning the Commercial Street School and the Buckle Street School. Signed by Claude G. Montefiore, E. Montefiore Nicholls. In English. [147] pp.; 24 cm.
  - Taḳanot: yeshanot ve-ḥadashot she-naasah bi-retson ha-manhige ha-ḳehilah uvi-retson kol ha-b.b. de-ḳehilatenu..., 565, [1805] (Box 3)
    Cover title: Rules & regulations. Liverpool. By-laws of the Liverpool synagogue agreed upon and signed by rabbis and officials of the synagogue. Pages numbered from 336 to 454. In Yiddish and Hebrew. 57 leaves; 31 cm.
  - Zeh ha-pinkas shayakh leha-havirah mishnayot meha-kloyz Linat ha-Tsedek; Pinkas kehilah shel Sharhorod, 1905-1908 (Box 4)
    Sharhorod, Ukraine. Rules, contributions, and membership of Mishnah study group. Ornate title page and borders. Signed and stamped by Rabbi Akiva Zabarsky ha-Kohen. Written and/or illustrated by Mosheh Kerman. In Hebrew. 35 cm.
  - A Diosgyori chevra kadischa jegyzokonyve, 1912 February 25-1942 February 24 (Box 5)
    Diosgyor, Hungary. Book of minutes with accounts and proceedings of the Hevra Kaddisha (charitable association)of Diosgyor, Hungary. Lists of income and expenses suggest that the served a broad social/charitable role. [94] leaves.
  - [Pinkas Mishnayot]; [Pinkas takanot shel hevrat Mishnayot]; [Pinkas kehilat Erdina?], [ca.1880] (Box 5)
    Erda?, Hungary? Description from vendor, Yeshayahu Vinograd: "Register of by-laws of the Mishnah Society,Erdina. On paper, 33 x 21 cm. Original antique leather cover, somewhat damaged. In the register are five pages of the society's by-laws and approx. twelve pages of the names decorated in color (some with calligraphy) of people with notes about each community member who belonged to the group, when he became a member, how much he paid, etc. Presumably this community is the one in Hungary, although there is one with a similar name in Germany." In Hebrew. Cardboard insert is most likely a scrap from bookbinding-- translation from Hungarian: [U]zleti. Business hours from 7 a.m. to 7 p.m. Sunday and holidays all rooms/shops are closed in the afternoon.
  - Mindszenti izraelita "Szent-Egylet" kozgyuleseinek jegyzokonyvei 1889ik evtol; [Pinkas hevrah-kadisha of Mindszent]., 1889-1902 (Box 5)
    Mindszent, Hungary. Minutes of general meetings of the Hevrah Kadisha (charitable association) of Mindszent, Hungary. Signed by rabbis and leaders of the Mindszent Jewish community, including an official red wax seal on one of the documents. In Hungarian. Approx. 80 pp.; 35 cm.
  - Protokoll von Todten, Trauungs, Geburts; [Pinkas kehilah shel Csaba, Hungary], 1851-1942 (Box 6)
    Csaba, Hungary. Register of births, marriages and deaths, with red wax seals and signed by Grand Rabbiner Efraim Braun and other officials. Introduction with by-laws of the community. In German and Hungarian, with some dates written in Hebrew. Register covers the years 1851-1875. A few miscellaneous letters and other documents (1911-1942) are inserted in book. 38 cm.
  - Szuletesi anyakonyv; Pinkas rishum kehilat Mishkolëtìs], 1895-1950 (Box 6)
    Miskolc and environs, Hungary. Two volumes. Register of births of Jewish children in Hungarian provincial cities and environs. In Hungarian with some Hebrew. Includes Hebrew and Hungarian names of child and parents, status of child according to Jewish law, circumcision information for boys. Vol. 1: Miskolc 1895-1921. Vol. 2: Onod and environs 1913-1938, 1943-1944, 1947, 1950.
  - [Pinkas kehilah shel Alberti Irsa], 1907-1938 (Box 7)
    Alberti-Irsa,Hungary. Various handwritten, printed, typewritten, and mimeographed documents bound together. Mainly in Hungarian. Over half are documents relating to the Jewish Community Council of Alberti-Irsa. The rest are miscellaneous documents from other cities and towns in Hungary. Includes the film script of the "Legend Rabbi Bar Bar Chana" and associated material. Written on title page: Az alb. irsai izr. el. Nepiskola I.II. osztalyu tanuloinak Nevsora Az 1907-8-i tanevrol (Register of names of the pupils in the first and second grades of the Israelite grade school of Alberti-Irsa in the 1907-1908 school year); also what appears to be a name, Kelsman Alberti; second line hard to read. Approx. 80 pp.; 36 cm.
  - [Szeged, Hungary: Collection of documents relating to the Jewish community], 1880-1939 (Box 7)
    Over 120 documents, almost all in Hungarian. Letters and communal records signed by Rabbi Immanuel Loew, a founder of the Neolog Reform movement in Hungary, and other important documents of both the Neolog and Orthodox communities in Szeged. Also includes drawings and plans of the Great Synagogue, which was built in 1905. 4 vols.; 36 cm.
  - [Minutes of the Hevrah Kadisha], 1911-1932 (Box 8)
    Reghin, Romania (Szaszregen, Hungary). Regulations and decisions concerning the Jewish community, the synagogue, synagogue officials, and charitable contributions. Minutes contain much material on the community and its leaders. Includes accounts of income and expenses. Covers period when this area changed from Hungarian to Romanian domain. In Hungarian and German, with some Hebrew words. [374] p.; 34 cm.
  - [Pinkas bet ha-yetomim be-Satu-Mare], 1946-1947 (Box 8)
    Satu-Mare, Romania. In Hebrew and Romanian, with lavishly decorated pages in gold ink listing donations to the Jewish orphanage in honor of children born 1946-1947. With illustrations signed by the artist. Approx. 30 leaves: ill., 31 cm.
  - [Pinkas kehilot Alzas], 1804-1818 (Box 9)
    Alsace, France. The notebook, dating from the time of Napoleon, contains records with income and expenses of various Jewish communities in the Alsace area, including many small and otherwise unknown communities. Taxes and other payments to government officials such as "geheshbund mit der medinah" and "karke gelt" are listed. [48] leaves; 19 cm.
  - [Ketav yad al kehilot Yehudiyot be-Eropah], [1808-1828?] (Box 9)
    Germany?/Austria?/Hungary? Collection of historical information on Jewish communities throughout Europe, their population, conditions, relations with the local authorities, etc., edited by an unidentified Jew from material gathered from newspapers and other sources. This register was from the collection of Professor S. H. Liber, a librarian at a museum in Prague. In Yiddish and German. 226 pp.; 25 cm.
  - Pinkas: zeh shayakh leha-hevrah Tehilim u-Vikur Holim shel be. Ha-kenes. Meydman Strit she-nityasdah bi-shenat 660., 660, [1900] (Box 10)
    London. Lists of contributions, memorial pages, by-laws of committee at London's Maidman Street synagogue. Large, high quality book with ornate, colorful calligraphy and paper-cuts. In Hebrew, Yiddish, and English. Approx. 30 pp.; 43 cm.
  - Ha[up]tbuch, 1884-1925 (Box 10)
    Budapest, Hungary. Ledger of accounts of members of the Jewish community of Budapest. In German and Hungarian. 294 pp.; 46 cm.
  - Szuletesi Anyakonyv 1852-1877: a kotet betuje: B; Geburts-Protokoll (Box 11)
    Bekescsaba, Hungary. Register of births of Jewish children in Bekescsaba, Hungary and environs. In German, Hungarian, and Hebrew. The "B" at the end of the title suggests that this may be the second volume of a set. With index. 229 leaves; 40 cm.
  - A Miskolczi Izraelita noegylet torzskonyve: 1878ik evi Aprilis 1tol, 1889-[1911] (Box 12)
    Miskolc, Hungary. Charter book of the Israelite Women's Association of Miskolcz, founded April 1, 1878. List of members, with married and maiden name, and where appropriate, date of death. Some names followed by comments, may her memory be a blessing (Aldott legyen emleke) or peace on her ashes (Beke poraira). After pages were filled on front, new members' names were added on backs of pages. With index in back. In Hungarian, with some Hebrew. 384, [22] pp.; 42 cm.
  - Szuletesi Anyakonyv 1871-1875, 1871-1947 (Box 12)
    Miskolc, Hungary. Register of births of Jewish children born in Miskolc, Hungary, from 1871 through 1875. Written in Hungarian and Hebrew, with pages printed in Hungarian, German, and Hebrew. Six other documents are inserted in back of book: application form from Joint Distribution Committee, 1945; form for "kivonat"--extract--birth certificate; Hebrew writing re: boy born in hospital; Hebrew certificate re: funds for synagogue, 5664 [1904]?; Bratislava, a document written in Czech or in Slovak; announcement of guest appearance of Warsaw Yiddish Theater, 1947. 57 leaves; 45 cm.
  - Pinkas; [Pinkas kehilat Mishkolts], 1835-1848 (Box 13)
    Miskolc, Hungary. Detailed list of all the Jews of Miskolc and the surrounding villages that owe the royal tax \(mas ha-melekh ha-meyuhad"\). There are various rulings concerning exemptions from the tax, including the signatures of rabbis of the various communities and their official wax seals. Some of the takanot are written in Yiddish. The title page is illuminated on paper which has been cut out and pasted into the book. Hungarian pages list those receiving support from the Israelite community of Miskolc: a) Havi sagely altal (through a monthly stipend) includes widows, students, the rabbi, and others; b) Tuzifaval (wood for heating); c) Pessachliszttel ("Pesach flour"); d) Alapitvanyokbol (from foundation.) List of those "who are worthy of support" includes two whose occupation is beggar. In Hungarian and Yiddish.
  - Schul-Kassa-Buch 1851, 1851-1852 (Box 13)
    Miskolc, Hungary. Bound book with loose pages in pocket. Book of accounts of Israelite boys' and girls' school, including lists of names of children and parents, with amounts of contributions and arrears. In Hungarian and German.
  - Brody fele vegrendelet; [Pinkas tsavaah ve-takanot bet ha-midrash shel R. Yosef Binyamin Zeev Brody], [between 1835 and 1840] (Box 13)
    Miskolc, Hungary. 1. Wills of Mordekhai Brody and Wolf Brodi written on blue paper in Yiddish. 2. Will of Wolf Brodi written on ivory paper mostly in German, with some Hebrew. Table of contents, written in Hungarian, indicates bequests to individuals and community, including providing for school, distribution of kindling, dowries, and the establishment of a scholarship. The wills include by-laws, customs, and other details of the house of study. 45 cm.
  - Registru de intrare si esire; [Register of incoming and outgoing matters]., 1940-1943 (Box 14)
    Orsova, Romania. Records of a wide variety of matters handled by the Jewish community of Orsova during the time of World War II. Includes communications from other Jewish communities in Transylvania and Bucharest. In Romanian. Approx. [100] pp.; 42 cm.
  - Protokoll uber die am 10 Februar 1935, 1935-1951 (Box 14)
    Orsova, Romania. Jewish communal register of Orsova, Romania. In German and Romanian. 159 pp.; 44 cm.
  - Protokoll uber die am 15 Juni 1922, 1922-1932 (Box 14)
    Reghin, Romania. Minutes of sessions of the Orthodox Israelite Cultural Community. During the period covered by this register, the community of Szaszregen, Hungary, became Reghin, Romania. In German. 538 pp.; 40 cm.
  - Keren Kayemet, 1902-1941 (Box 15)
    Hogyesz, Hungary. Authenticated copy of the original will and testament of the late Simon Fuhrmann, including an inventory of belongings and enumeration of apartments. Petition/application for funds (e.g. by Pepi Green). Balance sheets of the Keren Kayemet fund established by S. Fuhrmann. Includes by-laws, decisions, and mention of people and events in the Jewish community of Hogyesz, Hungary. Title page printed in Hungarian national colors. Original cover. In Hungarian. Also, single page inserted in book, but not related: Alapitvanyi Okirat = Document of founding-- a kind of will with the designation of beneficiaries. Hermann Lauttmann donating seats #112 in men's and women's sections of Sephardic Temple to Miskolc Mishnayot and the Talmud Torah Association in exchange for recitation of prayers and studies in his memory. 300 p. (48 handwritten pages; the rest are blank); 47 cm.
  - Comune di Lugo, 1903-1916 (Box 15)
    Lugo, Italy. Part I includes documents and decisions concerning the Jewish community of Lugo, not far from Ravenna, Italy. Part II includes accounts of the community's income and expenses. In Italian.
  - Pinkas: mi-bet tefilah he-hadash, 1892 (Box 16)